 [
    {
      "number": 1,
      "question": "Which of the following statements is not true of halogens?",
      "options": [
        "they exist in different physical states.",
        "they exist as diatomic molecules.",
        "their ionic radii decrease down the group.",
        "their melting and boiling points increase down the group."
      ],
      "answer": "their ionic radii decrease down the group."
    },
    {
      "number": 2,
      "question": "Elements in the same group of the periodic table have",
      "options": [
        "The same number of valence electrons",
        "the same number of electron shells.",
        "different chemical behaviour",
        "The same atomic size."
      ],
      "answer": "The same number of valence electrons"
    },
    {
      "number": 3,
      "question": "The following properties are characteristics of transition elements except",
      "options": [
        "formation of complexions.",
        "fixed oxidation states.",
        "formation of coloured compounds.",
        "catalytic abilities."
      ],
      "answer": "fixed oxidation states."
    },
    {
      "number": 4,
      "question": "An element Q forms a compound QCl5. In which group of the periodic table is Q?",
      "options": [
        "I",
        "III",
        "V",
        "VII"
      ],
      "answer": "V"
    },
    {
      "number": 5,
      "question": "Chlorine, bromine and iodine belong to the same group and",
      "options": [
        "are gaseous at room temperature.",
        "form white precipitate",
        "react violently with hydrogen without heating",
        "react with alkali."
      ],
      "answer": "react with alkali."
    },
    {
      "number": 6,
      "question": "Which of the following elements can conveniently be placed in two groups in the periodic table?",
      "options": [
        "carbon.",
        "copper.",
        "hydrogen.",
        "oxygen."
      ],
      "answer": "hydrogen."
    },
    {
      "number": 7,
      "question": "Which of the following halogens is solid at room temperature?",
      "options": [
        "bromine.",
        "Chlorine.",
        "fluorine",
        "iodine."
      ],
      "answer": "iodine."
    },
    {
      "number": 8,
      "question": "To which group and period respectively does an element with 15 electrons belong?",
      "options": [
        "3 and 3.",
        "3 and 5.",
        "5 and 3.",
        "5 and 5."
      ],
      "answer": "5 and 3."
    },
    {
      "number": 9,
      "question": "Which of the following elements is a d-block element?",
      "options": [
        "calcium.",
        "iron.",
        "lithium.",
        "silicon."
      ],
      "answer": "iron."
    },
    {
      "number": 10,
      "question": "Calcium and magnesium belong to the same group in the periodic table because both",
      "options": [
        "are metals.",
        "form cation.",
        "form colourless salts.",
        "have the same number of valence electrons."
      ],
      "answer": "have the same number of valence electrons."
    },
    {
      "number": 11,
      "question": "Which of the following elements is diatomic?",
      "options": [
        "iron",
        "neon",
        "oxygen",
        "sodium."
      ],
      "answer": "oxygen"
    },
    {
      "number": 12,
      "question": "If x is a group III element, its oxide would be represented as",
      "options": [
        "X3O2.",
        "X3O.",
        "X2O3.",
        "XO3."
      ],
      "answer": "X2O3."
    },
    {
      "number": 13,
      "question": "Which of the following gases is monatomic?",
      "options": [
        "argon.",
        "chlorine.",
        "nitrogen.",
        "oxygen."
      ],
      "answer": "argon."
    },
    {
      "number": 14,
      "question": "The element with electron configuration 1s² 2s² 2p⁶ 3s² 3p¹ belongs to",
      "options": [
        "s-block, period 3, group 1.",
        "p-block, period 3, group 2.",
        "s-block, period 3, group 3.",
        "p-block, period 3."
      ],
      "answer": "p-block, period 3."
    },
    {
      "number": 15,
      "question": "Which of the following halogens is liquid at room temperature?",
      "options": [
        "iodine.",
        "chlorine.",
        "bromine.",
        "fluorine."
      ],
      "answer": "bromine."
    },
    {
      "number": 16,
      "question": "Rare gases are stable because they",
      "options": [
        "are chemically active.",
        "contain equal number of protons and neutrons.",
        "contain more electrons than protons.",
        "have octet structures."
      ],
      "answer": "have octet structures."
    },
    {
      "number": 17,
      "question": "In the periodic table, alkaline earth metals can be found in group",
      "options": [
        "I.",
        "II.",
        "VI.",
        "VII."
      ],
      "answer": "II."
    },
    {
      "number": 18,
      "question": "A transition metal would be expected to",
      "options": [
        "form oxides with different formulae.",
        "have strong oxidizing ability.",
        "have low density.",
        "have an atomic structure with an incomplete outermost shell."
      ],
      "answer": "have an atomic structure with an incomplete outermost shell."
    },
    {
      "number": 19,
      "question": "Potassium and sodium show similar chemical properties because they I. belong to the same group in the Periodic Table II. have equal number of electrons in their outermost shells III. both exist in the +1 oxidation state in their compounds IV. belong to the same period in the Periodic Table",
      "options": [
        "IV only.",
        "I & II.",
        "III & IV.",
        "I, II & III."
      ],
      "answer": "I, II & III."
    },
    {
      "number": 20,
      "question": "The oxidation number of sulphur in Fe₂(SO₄)₃ is",
      "options": [
        "+2",
        "+3",
        "+4",
        "+6"
      ],
      "answer": "+6"
    },
    {
      "number": 21,
      "question": "Which of the following oxides of nitrogen has oxidation number of 1?",
      "options": [
        "KNO₃",
        "N₂O",
        "N₂O₃",
        "NO"
      ],
      "answer": "N₂O"
    },
    {
      "number": 22,
      "question": "The oxidation number of phosphorus in PO₄³⁻ is",
      "options": [
        "+1",
        "+2",
        "+3",
        "+5"
      ],
      "answer": "+5"
    },
    {
      "number": 23,
      "question": "The periodic table is an arrangement of elements according to their",
      "options": [
        "oxidation number.",
        "atomic number.",
        "mass number.",
        "number of neutrons."
      ],
      "answer": "atomic number."
    },
    {
      "number": 24,
      "question": "The group to which elements belong in the periodic table is determined by the number of",
      "options": [
        "electrons.",
        "core electrons.",
        "valence shells.",
        "valence electrons."
      ],
      "answer": "valence electrons."
    },
    {
      "number": 25,
      "question": "Which of the following arrangements indicates the correct decreasing order of ionization energy of period 3 elements?",
      "options": [
        "Na, Al, P, Cl.",
        "Cl, P, Al, Na.",
        "Na, P, Cl, Al.",
        "Al, Na, P, Cl."
      ],
      "answer": "Cl, P, Al, Na."
    },
    {
      "number": 26,
      "question": "The ionization energy is affected by the following factors except",
      "options": [
        "distance of the outermost electron(s) from the nucleus.",
        "size of the positive nuclear charge.",
        "ability to attract shared electron(s).",
        "screening effect of the inner electron(s)."
      ],
      "answer": "ability to attract shared electron(s)."
    },
    {
      "number": 27,
      "question": "Which of the following statements about the behaviour of the atom is correct?",
      "options": [
        "atomic size decreases down the group.",
        "atomic size increases across the period.",
        "anions are smaller than the parent atom.",
        "cations are smaller than the parent atom."
      ],
      "answer": "cations are smaller than the parent atom."
    },
    {
      "number": 28,
      "question": "Which of the following arrangement is in order of increasing ionization energy?",
      "options": [
        "Al, Si, P, S.",
        "Si, Al, S, P.",
        "S, P, Si, Al.",
        "P, Si, S, Al."
      ],
      "answer": "Al, Si, P, S."
    },
    {
      "number": 29,
      "question": "Which of the following arrangements shows increasing order of reactivity of the halogens?",
      "options": [
        "F₂ > Cl₂ > Br₂ > I₂.",
        "I₂ < Br₂ < Cl₂ < F₂.",
        "F₂ < Cl₂ < Br₂ < I₂.",
        "I₂ > Br₂ > Cl₂ > F₂."
      ],
      "answer": "I₂ < Br₂ < Cl₂ < F₂."
    },
    {
      "number": 30,
      "question": "The energy change that accompanies the addition of an electron to an isolated gaseous atom is",
      "options": [
        "atomization.",
        "electronegativity.",
        "electron affinity.",
        "ionization energy."
      ],
      "answer": "electron affinity."
    },
    {
      "number": 31,
      "question": "Which of the following arrangements is in order of increasing metallic property?",
      "options": [
        "Li < Na < K.",
        "Na < Li < K.",
        "K < Na < Li.",
        "K < Li < Na."
      ],
      "answer": "Li < Na < K."
    },
    {
      "number": 32,
      "question": "In which of the following series are the atoms arranged in order of increasing ionization energy?",
      "options": [
        "Li, Na, K.",
        "B, Be, Li.",
        "O, F, Ne.",
        "Be, Mg, Ca."
      ],
      "answer": "B, Be, Li."
    },
    {
      "number": 33,
      "question": "In which of the following atoms is the ionic radius larger than the atomic radius? [₁₁Na, ₁₂Mg, ₁₃Al, ₁₇Cl]",
      "options": [
        "aluminium.",
        "chlorine",
        "magnesium",
        "sodium."
      ],
      "answer": "magnesium"
    },
    {
      "number": 34,
      "question": "Which of the following statements about ionic radius is correct? Ionic radius",
      "options": [
        "increases as nuclear charge increase",
        "decrease as nuclear charge increases.",
        "decreases as nuclear charge decreases.",
        "remains constant as nuclear charge increase."
      ],
      "answer": "decrease as nuclear charge increases."
    },
    {
      "number": 35,
      "question": "The energy required to remove the most loosely bound electron from an atom in the gaseous state is known as the",
      "options": [
        "bond energy.",
        "ionization energy.",
        "potential energy.",
        "activation energy."
      ],
      "answer": "ionization energy."
    },
    {
      "number": 36,
      "question": "Which of the following decrease(s) from left to right across the period but increase(s) down the group in the periodic table? I. Ionization energy II. Electron affinity III. Electronegativity IV. Atomic radius",
      "options": [
        "IV only.",
        "I & II.",
        "III & IV.",
        "I, II & III."
      ],
      "answer": "IV only."
    },
    {
      "number": 37,
      "question": "Which of the following indicates the correct increasing order of oxidizing power of the halogens?",
      "options": [
        "F < Cl < Br < I.",
        "I < Br < Cl < F.",
        "I < Cl < Br < F.",
        "Br < F < I < Cl."
      ],
      "answer": "I < Br < Cl < F."
    },
    {
      "number": 38,
      "question": "Which of the following Group 1 elements has the highest ionization energy?",
      "options": [
        "⁵⁵Cs.",
        "³⁷Rb.",
        "¹⁹K.",
        "³Li."
      ],
      "answer": "³Li."
    },
    {
      "number": 39,
      "question": "Consider the reaction represented by the equation: 2H₂SO₄(aq) + C(s) → 2H₂O(l) + 2SO₂(g) + CO₂(g). H₂SO₄ is acting as",
      "options": [
        "a catalyst",
        "an oxidizing agent",
        "a reducing agent",
        "a sulphonating agent"
      ],
      "answer": "an oxidizing agent"
    },
    {
      "number": 40,
      "question": "Which of the following metals is the strongest reducing agent?",
      "options": [
        "sodium",
        "silver",
        "potassium",
        "copper"
      ],
      "answer": "potassium"
    },
    {
      "number": 41,
      "question": "Reduction is the process of",
      "options": [
        "loss of electron",
        "loss of hydrogen",
        "loss of oxygen",
        "addition of electronegative element"
      ],
      "answer": "loss of electron"
    },
    {
      "number": 42,
      "question": "When an atom gains an electron, it becomes",
      "options": [
        "chemically inactive",
        "negatively charged",
        "oxidized",
        "a carbon"
      ],
      "answer": "negatively charged"
    },
    {
      "number": 43,
      "question": "Which of the following substances is not a reducing agent?",
      "options": [
        "C",
        "CO",
        "O₂",
        "H₂"
      ],
      "answer": "O₂"
    },
    {
      "number": 44,
      "question": "How many orbitals are associated with the d-sub energy level?",
      "options": [
        "2",
        "3",
        "5",
        "7"
      ],
      "answer": "5"
    },
    {
      "number": 45,
      "question": "Which of the following ions has the electron configuration 2, 8, 8?",
      "options": [
        "Na⁺",
        "Mg²⁺",
        "F⁻",
        "Cl⁻"
      ],
      "answer": "Mg²⁺"
    },
    {
      "number": 46,
      "question": "An element with the electron configuration of 1s² 2s² 2p⁶ would have a combining power of",
      "options": [
        "0",
        "2",
        "8",
        "6"
      ],
      "answer": "0"
    },
    {
      "number": 47,
      "question": "An element has electronic configuration 1s² 2s² 2p⁶ 3s² 3p⁴. To what period does it belong in the periodic table?",
      "options": [
        "3",
        "6",
        "4",
        "5"
      ],
      "answer": "3"
    },
    {
      "number": 48,
      "question": "Which of the following substances is a non-electrolyte?",
      "options": [
        "H₂SO₄",
        "CH₃COOH",
        "C₆H₁₂O₆",
        "NH₄Cl"
      ],
      "answer": "C₆H₁₂O₆"
    },
    {
      "number": 49,
      "question": "The electrons that are mostly removed from ²⁴₁₂Mg are in which orbital?",
      "options": [
        "1s",
        "2s",
        "2p",
        "3s"
      ],
      "answer": "3s"
    },
    {
      "number": 50,
      "question": "How many unpaired electrons are there in an atom of element having 1s² 2s² 2p⁶?",
      "options": [
        "1",
        "0",
        "2",
        "6"
      ],
      "answer": "0"
    }
  ]
